<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A declaration for peace from the Kings most Excellent Majesty, and the dukes, marquesses, bishops, earles, lords, knights, and the rest of his commissioners at Newport; to be published throughout the kingdom of England, and dominion of VVales; containing, their unanimous resolutions for an agreement with both houses of Parliament, within the time (of 40 dayes) limited for the treaty; and His gracious and finall answer to the paper of Ireland, presented to the commissioners on Friday last. With their happy and joyfull agreement therein. Dated at Newport 14 Octob. 1648. Subscribed Charles Rex.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 11 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78701</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C2201</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E468_5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R205325</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864734</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864734</idno>
            <idno type="VID">116966</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78701)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 116966)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 75:E468[5])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A declaration for peace from the Kings most Excellent Majesty, and the dukes, marquesses, bishops, earles, lords, knights, and the rest of his commissioners at Newport; to be published throughout the kingdom of England, and dominion of VVales; containing, their unanimous resolutions for an agreement with both houses of Parliament, within the time (of 40 dayes) limited for the treaty; and His gracious and finall answer to the paper of Ireland, presented to the commissioners on Friday last. With their happy and joyfull agreement therein. Dated at Newport 14 Octob. 1648. Subscribed Charles Rex.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 6 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>for R. Smith, neer Temple-Bar,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A newsletter; not an official document.</note>
                  <note>With a title-page woocut.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "8ber [i.e. October] 17th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Monarchy --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:116966:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:116966:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DECLARATION FOR PEACE From the Kings moſt Excellent Majeſty, and the Dukes, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſes, Biſhops, Earles, Lords, Knights, and the reſt of His <hi>Commiſſioners</hi> at <hi>Newport;</hi> to be publiſhed throughout the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> and Dominion of <hi>VVales;</hi> Containing, their unanimous Reſolutions for an Agreement with both Houſes of Parliament, within the time (of 40 dayes) limited for the <hi>Treaty; And His Gracious and Finall Anſwer to the paper of</hi> Ireland, preſented to the <hi>Commiſſioners</hi> on <hi>Friday</hi> laſt. With their happy and joyfull <hi>Agreement</hi> therein.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dated at Newport</hi> 14 <hi>Octobe</hi> 1648. Subſcribed <hi>CHARLES REX.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <head>The <hi>Treaty</hi> at <hi>Newport.</hi> Peace be amongſt you.</head>
               <figDesc>throned man (from context, Charles I) on platform, with notaries, and surrounded by male listeners</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Imprinted at <hi>London,</hi> for <hi>R. Smith,</hi> neer Temple-Bar, 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:116966:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:116966:2"/>
            <head>A DECLARATION FOR PEACE, From the Kings moſt Excellent Majeſty, and the <hi>Dukes, Marqueſses, Biſhops, Earles, Lords, Knights,</hi> and the reſt of the Commiſſioners for the <hi>Treaty.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">Incloſed in a Letter from the Iſle of <hi>Wight,</hi> to be forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with printed, and publiſhed throughout the ſeverall reſpective Counties within the Kingdom of England, and Dominion of <hi>Wales.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honorable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THis preſent Treaty is conceived to be the main Object of the whole Kingdom, whoſe eyes are fixed thereupon, expecting the happy tydings
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:116966:3"/>of Peace, to be ſent forth by the bleſſed <hi>Dove</hi> with an Olive branch in her mouth, throughout all the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the Nation; and (in all probability) they are now ready to iſſue forth in ſtreames of joy, to water the Plants of this late flouriſhing and fruitfull Iſland.</p>
            <p>For his Majeſty (upon a conference with the <hi>Dukes Marqueſses; Biſhops, Earles, Lords,</hi> and the reſt of the <hi>Commiſſioners</hi> on his part) hath declared his unanimous Reſolution for a mutuall agreement and compliance with his two Houſes of Parliament, to all things by them deſired, which may tend to the peace and ſafety of all his liege people throughout his Realmes and Dominions.</p>
            <p>And upon Thurſday laſt delivered his gracious an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer and Royall Aſſent to the Commiſſioners at the Treaty, to the paper of <hi>Ireland,</hi> in all things by them deſired, which was as followeth.</p>
            <p>That his Majeſty doth condeſcend, That an Act of Parliament be paſſed, to declare and make void the Ceſſation of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and all treaties and concluſion of peace, or any articles thereupon with the Rebels, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out conſent of both Houſes.</p>
            <p>And that according to their Deſire, He is pleaſed to ſettle the proſecution of the war in that <hi>Kingdome</hi> in his two Houſes, to be managed by them: and that He is willing to aſſiſt and adhere to them therein, promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing upon his Royall Word to do no Act to diſcoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance or moleſt them.</p>
            <p>To the ſecond clauſe therein inſerted, His Majeſty doth agree, That Reformation of Religion according
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:116966:3"/>to the Covenant be ſetled in that Kingdom by Act of Parliament, in ſuch manner as both his two Houſes have agreed, or ſhall agree upon, after conſultation had with the Aſſembly of Divines ſitting at Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter.</p>
            <p>To the third Clauſe, His Majeſty giveth this An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, That he will give His Conſent that the Deputy Governour or Governours, and the Preſidents of the ſeverall provinces of that <hi>Kingdome,</hi> be nominated by his two Houſes of the Parliament of <hi>England;</hi> as alſo all other Offices whatſoever; being limited for twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty years from the 1 of <hi>July</hi> 1648.</p>
            <p>This Anſwer ſeemed very ſatiſfactory, and upon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt thereof the Commiſſioners preſented a paper to his <hi>Maieſty</hi> for payment of the publique Debts of the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> which cauſed a large <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ebate upon <hi>Friday;</hi> and after ſeverall <hi>Arguments</hi> laid down by the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners</hi> on both ſides, the King promiſed to give a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Anſwer the next day.</p>
            <p>And for the reſt of the Propoſitions, there's no doubt but a ſpeedy concurrence will be given to them all; for the Nobility and Clergy on the Kings ſide have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to his <hi>Majesty</hi> for peace; his <hi>Maieſty</hi> concurs with them therein and hath promiſed to diſpenſe with Epiſcopacy, and to ſettle the Directory, rather then to leave his people unſatiſfied, or involve them in a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther effuſion, or ſtreams of bloud.</p>
            <p>And the <hi>Parliament Commiſſioners goe hand in hand with them, promiſing to leave no means unattempted that may conduce to the peace and ſafety of all his Maieſties Realms and Dominions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Newport 14. Octob. 1648.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:116966:4"/>
            <p>By Letters from the Iſle of <hi>Wight Octob.</hi> 14. it is ſaid. That his Majeſty hath had ſome further conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation with the Commiſſioners of both Houſes, and deſires that all obſtructions may be removed; that may retard ſo bleſſed a work, promiſing to leave no means unattempted, for the ſetling of a firm and laſting peace throughout his Realms and Dominion; and the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to ſatisfie his two Houſes of <hi>Parliament,</hi> he hath been graciouſly pleaſed to paſſe the Bill for recalling all his <hi>Decclarations</hi> and <hi>Proclamations,</hi> publiſhed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt either or both Houſes of <hi>Parliament;</hi> as alſo, the Bill for confirming the <hi>Militia</hi> in the power of <hi>Parliament</hi> for 20 yeers; promiſing upon his Royall word to enact the ſame, and all other Bills or Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions whatſoever, that ſhall be agreed upon by his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, and the Commiſſioners of both Houſes of <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And it is reported at Court, that the <hi>King</hi> hath ſent a Letter to the Lord Gen. <hi>Fairfax,</hi> and Lieut. Generall <hi>Cromwell,</hi> viz.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Deſiring them to uſe all means poſſible for the propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of this preſent Treaty, and to indeavour the ſetling of a firm and laſting peace throughout his bleeding and diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>racted Kingdoms; that ſo all his liege people of what ſect or ſort ſoever, may no longer feel the cruelty and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of a moſt bloudy and inteſtine war, but (after a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven years Pilgrimage in deſolation and confuſion) for the future, enjoy a true and evelaſting peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And truly, I am confident, that no man deſires peace more then his Majeſty, but yet ſcruples at the <hi>Directo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> and argueth ſtifly for <hi>Epiſcopacy;</hi> as appears by his enſuing anſwer to the <hi>Propoſition</hi> touching the Church of <hi>England</hi> as followeth.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:116966:4"/>
            <p>As to the Exceptions that his <hi>Maj.</hi> ſaid nothing to the conſenting to a Bill for the aboliſhing of Arch-bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, &amp;c, nor that the Ordinance for aboliſhing them be confirmed by Act of <hi>Parl.</hi> the Form of Church go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and Directory for worſhip which you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to him, and thereby hath eſtabliſhed the actuall poſſeſſion, and publike exerciſe of theſe Forms, &amp; hath ſuſpended the preſent Government and Form of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip eſtabliſhed by law, but deſired a coſultation with Divines in the mean time for a future ſettlement, is in that paper is expreſſed: His Maj. therefore declares, that the reaſon why he did not anſwer to that part of your Propoſition was, becauſe he was not ſatisfied in his conſcience; He can be content to the utter aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of Epiſcopacy: the ſubſtance whereof hee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives to conſiſt in the power of Ordination and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as they were exerciſed by the Apoſtles them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and others, by authority derived from them, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior to Presbyters &amp; Deaco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in the primitive times: but becauſe he acknowledgeth that Biſhops were to have councel and aſſiſtance of Presbyters in Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Juriſdiction, and in the laſt were, and are limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Civill power, his Maj. Deſired the conſulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with the Divines, to the end that he and his two Houſes might determine in what manner Ordination and Juriſdiction might be moderated and regulated for the future government of the Church, His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Reſolution being to comply with his two houſes for the alteration and regulating of his preſent Hierar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy and Government, ſo as Epiſcopacy reduced to the Primitive uſage may be ſetled and continued in this Church: and therefore his Maj. heartily deſires their concurrence in the one, that he may with more free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom give his aſſent to the other.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:116966:5"/>
            <p>As to the Exception, that his Maj. hath not expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his conſent for ſetling of Biſhops Lands upon tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtees, and for the ſale of thoſe lands, its true, he hath not to alienate the Inheritance of thoſe lands, and herein he believes he hath concurrent opinions of many Divines, that in order points differ much among themſelves but his former anſwer containing a large offer of ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to al thoſe that have purchaſed, or disburſed mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies upon thoſe lands, he hopes that anſwer, to which he now refers, will be ſatisfactory to his two houſes.</p>
            <p>His Maj. will confirm the publike uſe of the <hi>Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory</hi> in all Churches and Chappels, and will conſent to the repeal of ſo much of all ſtatutes, as only con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns the Book of <hi>Common-prayer,</hi> and alſo to the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the ſame away out of all Churches and Chapels; provided that the uſe thereof may be continued in his Maj. Chappell, for himſelf and his Houſhold.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Subſcribed CHARLES REX.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <opener>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Munday</hi>
                     <date>
                        <hi>Octob.</hi> 16.</date> 
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>Letters from the Iſle of Wight ſay, <hi>That his Majeſty is (in part) convinced of the Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours of Epiſcopacy, and will ſpeedily give His Royall aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent for the ſetling of the Presbyterian Government, throughout the Kingdoms of</hi> England <hi>and</hi> Ireland, <hi>and Principality of</hi> Wales; <hi>ſo that there is no doubt, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the</hi> 40 <hi>dayes limited for the Treaty are expired, there will be a finall end and agreement between the King and Parliament.</hi>
               </p>
            </postscript>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:116966:5"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
